Guide to the New-York Historical Society Portrait Collection, circa 1640-2020 (bulk, 1800-1950) PR 52
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society portrait collection
circa 1640-2020 (bulk, 1800-1950)
New-York Historical Society
PR 52
125 Linear feet (177 boxes; 71 drawers of flat files)
Collection consists of circa 45,000 prints and photographs of varying format and media, from ordinary black-and-white engravings based on paintings to rare hand-colored mezzotints, and from posed, professional studio photographs to informal snapshots. Likenesses of American men who achieved national fame before 1930 predominate. There are also numerous images of prominent New Yorkers, theatrical personalities, eminent Europeans who figure in United States history, and views of birthplaces, tombs, statues, and associated items. Includes many portraits of American presidents through Franklin D. Roosevelt, of poet Walt Whitman, and other celebrities of the 1800s. People or organizations whose papers or artwork are at the New-York Historical Society tend to be well-represented, including statesman Albert Gallatin, sculptor John Rogers, the Seventh Regiment of the New York National Guard, hotel association members, and the Salmagundi Club. Several large collections are dispersed in the file by sitters' names: thousands of portraits culled chiefly from illustrated books and donated by Robert Fridenberg and circa 250 prints by Albert and Max Rosenthal of celebrated historical figures.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series:
Series I.
Individuals and Family Groups
Series II.
Groups
Series III.
Royalty
Series IV.
Unidentified
Items in the container list designated [crossed out] were marked thus on a paper copy of the original (2003) finding aid to the collection, and are possibly misfiled or missing.
Conditions Governing Access
For more information on making arrangements to consult the collection, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Portrait Collection was accumulated over time, primarily during the 20th century, from a variety of sources, including
• Edmund Bramhall Child (1846–1946).
• Robert Fridenberg, who donated thousands of portraits culled chiefly from illustrated books.
• Henry O. Havemeyer (1847–1907). Many of the prints in Subseries I.B and I.C came from his collection.
• Samuel Verplanck Hoffman (1866–1942), whose copy of Men of Affairs is found in Subseries I.E.
• Daniel Parish Jr. (1838–1914), a collector who was a long-time and regular donor to the Historical Society. On May 15, 1906 alone he gave "1,754 Prints, consisting of portraits (many of them are book plates and cut from Illustrated Newspapers)."
• Max Rosenthal (1833–1918) and Albert Rosenthal (1863–1939), circa 250 prints of celebrated historical figures.
• William Ives Rutter Jr., who gave a large collection of family portraits.
A significant part of this collection consists of portraits separated over time from their original provenance in personal and family papers held in the New-York Historical Society's manuscript department, a practice followed until, perhaps, the late 20th century.
Related Materials
Additional portraits of New Yorkers and other Americans can be found in many of the Department's collections including:
• Jessie Tarbox Beals Photograph Collection (PR 004)
• Carte de Visite Photograph File (PR 011)
• Cased Image File (PR 012)
• Arnold Genthe Photograph Collection (PR 019)
• Henry O. Havemeyer Collection of Portrait Prints of American Statesmen (PR 025)
• Theron W. Kilmer Portrait Photograph Collection (PR 030)
• Pirie MacDonald Portrait Photograph Collection (PR 039)
• Burr McIntosh Photograph Collection (PR 041)
• Stereograph File (PR 065)
• George E. Stonebridge Photograph Collection (PR 066)
• Doris Ulmann Photograph Collection (PR 072)
• Pach Brothers Portrait Photograph Collection (PR 084)
• Mathew B. Brady Studio Portrait Photograph Collection (PR 085)
• Maritime History Collection (PR 100)
• Jacques Reich Portrait Print Collection (PR 102)
• Theatrical Portraits File (PR 104)
Scope and Contents
The Portrait Collection (a.k.a. the Portrait File) contains prints and photographs which were taken or made as portraits of people. Portraits acquired by the New-York Historical Society have simply been filed alphabetically by sitter for decades; this finding aid is an attempt to give greater access to the collection. The collection is divided into four series: Individuals and Family Groups; Groups; Royalty; and Unidentified. Thereunder, each series has been further organized by size in order to provide adequate housing and conservation of the material. Family groups as well as individuals can be found in Series I; groups of unrelated people can be found in Series II. European Royalty can be found in Series III. Portraits in which a name was illegible, as well as those on which no name was inscribed, can be found in Series IV. The Portrait File contains examples of many different formats of photography, most notably cabinet cards, snapshots, and studio portraits. Etchings, engravings, lithographs, and photomechanical prints are included as well. Portraits included here are from many dates, although most date from the nineteenth and early twentieth century. One notable early portrait of Jacobus Critonius (identified as James Crichton) was cut from a 1640 issue of Museum Historicum. Early portrait photography includes a photograph of John C. Fremont, taken by Root in 1855; the file includes an accompanying print made after the photo. In some cases, there is a great quantity of portraits of one person. In general many portraits exist for American presidents, Civil War generals, and New York City mayors. In another example, nineteen portraits of George Monck (1608-1670), the Duke of Albermarle, are present.
Series I. Individuals and Family Groups is divided in five subseries: Small, Medium, Large, and Oversize formats, and plates from the book Men of Affairs. In each subseries except the last, the portraits are filed alphabetically by sitter's surname. As cross-references between subseries do not exist, researchers should be sure to check for a name in each (e.g., images of George Washington are found in small, medium, large, and oversize formats). Filing rules were established and were followed for all subseries where relevant. In general, women are filed under their married names, if known, and then their first names, if known. Names beginning in "Saint" are filed in S miscellaneous in between "Sah" and "Saj." Names beginning in "Mc" or "Mac" are filed together before other M names. British nobility are filed, as noted above, alphabetically. In general, a place name acts as the surname. For example, William Cavendish, Duke of Portland is filed under "Portland, Victor Frederick William Cavendish-Bentinck, Duke of." Edward Hyde, Earl of Clarendon, is filed under "Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of." While most persons pictured in this series are Americans, and particularly New Yorkers, the following historical figures do appear: Julius Caesar, Saint Cecelia, Alexander the Great, Galileo, Jesus, and Cupido, the Hottentot Evangelist. Portraits of E. B. Child, who was also a major donor to this collection, can be found in the Theatrical Portrait File as well as here (childhood portraits and pictures of his gravestone).
• Subseries I.A. Individuals and Family Groups: Small Format contains portraits that are smaller than 9 by 14 inches and are housed in boxes. Surnames or individuals with more than five images have their own folders. Those with less than five images are filed in alphabetical "miscellaneous" files. If a specific name is being sought and it does not appear in the container list, the miscellaneous files should be consulted. Photographs of New York mayor John V. Lindsay include some of him performing in a 1938 production of George Bernard Shaw's "The Devil's Disciple," put on by the St. Paul's School Dramatic Club. The Harold Applegate folder has photographs of Mr. Applegate in a dancing costume he wore in an 1899 carnival at his dancing school class, along with the program for the event. The N-YHS Museum owns the costume he wore in the carnival and the photograph. The Harry Scherman folder includes a homemade book in which identical photographs of Scherman are decorated with different cutouts of hats. A photograph of artist Thomas Nast shows a corner of his studio. Several eighteenth and nineteenth century engravings show Charles Howard, Earl of Nottingham (1536–1624), Lord High Admiral, England. A portrait of George Washington printed on silk was created for the bicentennial of his birth. A small-sized memorial card for Maria Jane Hurd, who died in Springfield, Massachusetts on March 12, 1849, is printed with an oval portrait of her.
• Subseries I.B. Individuals and Family Groups: Medium Format includes portraits that are housed in flat file drawers. Portraits in this subseries are between the sizes of 9 by 14 and 20 by 24 inches. All images are filed alphabetically, with list access provided to every sitter's name. Sitters with their own folders have been so denoted. Folders of surnames have also been denoted in this way. John Ogilvie is pictured in an early mezzotint from 1775. Several other American print portraits date from circa 1776. An early photograph shows the photographer Sarony. Several sets of portraits have been dispersed throughout this subseries. The Century Gallery of One Hundred Portraits, mainly prints of Americans noted for their contributions to arts and letters, was issued in 1886. A City College of New York class album from circa 1860 contains photographs of the graduates; the sitters are denoted by "CCNY" after their names. Portraits of American presidents often contain notable items. Memorials to Abraham Lincoln printed on silk are included here. Broadsides containing suggestions for how to advertise for memorials to President Theodore Roosevelt are included under his name.
• Subseries I.C. Individuals and Family Groups: Large Format includes portraits that are housed in flat file drawers. Portraits in this subseries are between the sizes of 20 x 24 and 24 x 40 inches. All images are filed alphabetically, with list access provided to every sitter's name. Sitters with their own folders have been so denoted. Folders of surnames have also been denoted in this way. Many of these large images are portraits of Civil War generals lithographed by the Kurz & Allison firm. A photograph of New York governor William Sulzer is set into an oversize display menu made for a dinner given by the Lotus Club of New York on February 8, 1913.
• Subseries I.D. Individuals and Family Groups: Oversize Format includes very large portraits that are housed in flat file drawers. Portraits in this subseries are larger than 24 x 40 inches. All images are filed alphabetically, with list access provided to every sitter's name. Sitters with their own folders have been so denoted. Folders of surnames have also been denoted in this way.
Series II. Groups is divided in four subseries: Small, Medium, Large, and Oversize formats. Portraits are grouped thereunder by broad subjects: Clubs and Organizations; Commercial Activities; Education; Entertainment; Health and Safety; Military; Politics and Government; Religion; and Other. Many photographs in this series show formal dinners held at various New York hotels. Several panoramic photographs can also be found here, including some of dinner guests.
Series III. Royalty is comprised of members of royal families, mainly European. Those who were born into a royal family were considered to be royalty, while those who took on similar titles through conquest, such as Napoleon, the "Emperor of France," were not considered royalty. This series is divided into three subseries: Small, Large, and Oversize formats. Portraits are arranged thereunder by country and then alphabetically (generally by the given name of the King or Queen).
• Subseries III.B. Royalty: Large Format includes portraits that are larger than 9.5 by 11 inches and smaller than 24 by 40 inches, including those sized as "Medium Format" in the preceding two series.
Series IV. Unidentified is arranged by gender, and thereunder by format. Groups are arranged by subject as in Series II. "Large Format" includes portraits that are larger than 9.5 by 11 inches and smaller than 24 by 40 inches, including those sized as "Medium Format" in the preceding two series.
Accruals
The Portrait Collection remains open for additional single items or small sets of related photographs and other images obtained by gift or purchase.
Separated Materials
From time to time, material in the Portrait Collection that is determined to have been separated in the past from its original place in personal or family manuscript collections, will be removed and returned to that manuscript collection.
Engravings (prints); Etchings (prints); Group portraits.; Mezzotints (prints); Photographs.; Portraits.; Prints (visual works); Birthplaces.; Celebrities -- New York (State) -- New York -- Portraits.; Celebrities -- United States -- Portraits.; Costume -- United States.; Hotelkeepers -- United States -- Portraits.; Presidents -- United States -- Portraits.; Soldiers -- New York (State) -- New York -- Portraits.; Statues.; Tombs.; New York (State). National Guard. Regiment, 7th; Salmagundi Club; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849. -- Portraits; Rogers, John, 1829-1904 -- Portraits; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892 -- Portraits
- Series I. Individuals and Family Groups
  Arrangement
  "Series I. Individuals and Family Groups" is divided in five subseries:
  Subseries I.A.
  Individuals and Family Groups: Small Format
  Subseries I.B.
  Individuals and Family Groups: Medium Format
  Subseries I.C.
  Individuals and Family Groups: Large Format
  Subseries I.D.
  Individuals and Family Groups: Oversize Format
  Subseries I.E.
  Men of Affairs
  In each subseries (except for the last), the portraits are filed alphabetically by sitter. Subseries I.A (small) format is housed in boxes; surnames or individuals with more than five images have their own folders and are listed below. The identified sitters in Subseries I.B (medium), I.C (large), and I.D (oversize) formats are housed in flat file drawers. Every name in these three subseries is listed. Those individuals having separate folders are so marked. Subseries I.E contains 360 small-size portraits from two copies of the book Men of Affairs.
  - Subseries I.A. Individuals and Family Groups: Small Format
    - Aa-Az miscellaneous (13 folders) (Offsite-box 1)
    - Abbott (Offsite-box 2)
    - Abercrombie (Offsite-box 2)
    - Abt, Franz (Offsite-box 2)
    - Adams (Offsite-box 2)
    - Adams, Abigail (Offsite-box 2)
    - Adams, Charles Francis (Offsite-box 2)
    - Adams, John (Offsite-box 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Portraits of
      Residence of
    - Adams, John Quincy (Offsite-box 2)
    - Adams, Samuel (Offsite-box 2)
    - Addison (Offsite-box 2)
    - Agassiz, Louis (Offsite-box 2)
    - Agnew (Offsite-box 2)
    - Alcott (Offsite-box 2)
    - Alden (Offsite-box 2)
    - Aldrich (Offsite-box 2)
    - Alexander (Offsite-box 3)
    - Alexander, James W. (Offsite-box 3)
    - Alexander, James and Mary (Offsite-box 3)
    - Alger, Russell A. (Offsite-box 3)
    - Allen (4 folders) (Offsite-box 3)
    - Allen, Henry T. (Offsite-box 3)
    - Allen, Stephen M. (Offsite-box 3)
    - Allison (Offsite-box 3)
    - Allston, Washington (Offsite-box 3)
    - Ames (Offsite-box 4)
    - Ames, Fisher (Offsite-box 4)
    - Amherst, Jeffrey, Lord (Offsite-box 4)
    - Anderson (Offsite-box 4)
    - Anderson, Alexander (Offsite-box 4)
    - Anderson, John E. (Offsite-box 4)
    - Anderson, Robert (Offsite-box 4)
    - Anderson, Robert H. (Offsite-box 4)
    - Andre, John (Offsite-box 4)
      Drawings by
      Monuments to
      Scenes from life of
      Miscellaneous
    - Andrew (Offsite-box 5)
    - Andrew, John A. (Offsite-box 5)
    - Andrews (Offsite-box 5)
    - Andrews, A. H. (Offsite-box 5)
    - Andros, Edmund (Offsite-box 5)
    - Anson, George, Lord (Offsite-box 5)
    - Anthony (Offsite-box 5)
    - Applegate, Harold R. (Offsite-box 5)
    - Appleton (Offsite-box 5)
    - Archer (Offsite-box 5)
    - Armstrong (Offsite-box 5)
    - Arnold (Offsite-box 5)
    - Arnold, Benedict (Offsite-box 5)
    - Arnold, Peggy Shippen (Offsite-box 5)
    - Arthur (Offsite-box 5)
    - Arthur, Chester A. (Offsite-box 5)
    - Ashley (Offsite-box 6)
    - Astor, John Jacob (1763-1848) (Offsite-box 6)
    - Astor, John Jacob II (1791-1869 (Offsite-box 6)
    - Astor, John Jacob III (1822-1890) (Offsite-box 6)
    - Astor, John Jacob IV (1864-1912) and Ava Willing (Offsite-box 6)
    - Astor, Nancy Langhorne Shaw (Offsite-box 6)
    - Astor, William Backhouse (1792-1875) (Offsite-box 6)
    - Astor, William Backhouse, Jr. (1830-1892) and Caroline Schemerhorn (Offsite-box 6)
    - Astor, William Waldorf (1848-1919) and Mary Paul (Offsite-box 6)
    - Atwood (Offsite-box 6)
    - Audubon, John J. (Offsite-box 6)
    - Averill, William W. (Offsite-box 6)
    - Avery (Offsite-box 6)
    - Axtell (Offsite-box 6)
    - Ayer (Offsite-box 6)
    - Ayres (Offsite-box 6)
    - Ayme (Offsite-box 6)
    - Ba-Bz miscellaneous (50 folders) (Offsite-box 7)
    - Babcock (Offsite-box 12)
    - Bache (Offsite-box 12)
    - Backus (Offsite-box 12)
    - Bacon (Offsite-box 12)
    - Badger (Offsite-box 12)
    - Bagg, Clinton Levi (Offsite-box 12)
    - Bagoe (Offsite-box 12)
    - Bailey (Offsite-box 12)
    - Bailey, Theodorus (Offsite-box 12)
    - Bainbridge (Offsite-box 12)
    - Baird (Offsite-box 12)
    - Baker (Offsite-box 12)
    - Baker, Edward D. (Offsite-box 12)
    - Baker, William B. and Josephine (Offsite-box 12)
    - Baldwin (Offsite-box 12)
    - Ball (Offsite-box 12)
    - Ballou (Offsite-box 12)
    - Bancroft (Offsite-box 12)
    - Bancroft, George (Offsite-box 12)
    - Banks, Nathaniel P. (Offsite-box 12)
    - Barber (Offsite-box 13)
    - Barbour (Offsite-box 13)
    - Barclay, McClelland (Offsite-box 13)
    - Barlow (Offsite-box 13)
    - Barlow, Joel (Offsite-box 13)
    - Barnard (Offsite-box 13)
    - Barnes (Offsite-box 13)
    - Barney (Offsite-box 13)
    - Barnum, Phineas T. (Offsite-box 13)
    - Barry, John (Offsite-box 13)
    - Bartlett (Offsite-box 13)
    - Barton, Clara (Offsite-box 13)
    - Bates (Offsite-box 14)
    - Bayard (Offsite-box 14)
    - Baxter (Offsite-box 14)
    - Beach (Offsite-box 14)
    - Bean (Offsite-box 14)
    - Beard (Offsite-box 14)
    - Beauregard, G. T. (Offsite-box 14)
    - Beck (Offsite-box 14)
    - Beckwith, James Carroll (Offsite-box 14)
    - Bedford (Offsite-box 14)
    - Beecher family (Offsite-box 14)
    - Beecher, Henry Ward (2 folders) (Offsite-box 14)
    - Beekman (Offsite-box 15)
    - Beekman, Henry Rutgers (Offsite-box 15)
    - Beekman, James William (Offsite-box 15)
    - Beekman, William (Offsite-box 15)
    - Belknap (Offsite-box 15)
    - Bell (Offsite-box 15)
    - Bell, John (Offsite-box 15)
    - Belmont (Offsite-box 15)
    - Belmont, August (Offsite-box 15)
    - Belmont, Caroline Perry (Offsite-box 15)
    - Belmont, Perry (Offsite-box 15)
    - Benedict (Offsite-box 15)
    - Benjamin (Offsite-box 15)
    - Bennett (Offsite-box 15)
    - Bennett, James G. (Offsite-box 15)
    - Benson (Offsite-box 16)
    - Benson, Egbert (Offsite-box 16)
    - Benton (Offsite-box 16)
    - Benton, Thomas H. (Offsite-box 16)
    - Berman, Rita (Offsite-box 16)
    - Bernheimer, Charles and Clara (Offsite-box 16)
      Separated Materials
      The Bernheimer photos were returned to the Charles Bernheimer papers (MS 58) from which they had been separated. June 2019
    - Berry (Offsite-box 16)
    - Berry, Edward (Offsite-box 16)
    - Bicknell, Frank A. (Offsite-box 16)
    - Biddle (Offsite-box 16)
    - Billows, Ray (Offsite-box 16)
    - Bingham (Offsite-box 16)
    - Birney (Offsite-box 16)
    - Bishop (Offsite-box 16)
    - Bismarck, Otto Furst von (Offsite-box 16)
    - Bissell (Offsite-box 16)
    - Black (Offsite-box 17)
    - Blackstone (Offsite-box 17)
    - Blaine, James G., and wife (Offsite-box 17)
    - Blair (Offsite-box 17)
    - Blair, Frank P. (Offsite-box 17)
    - Blake (Offsite-box 17)
    - Bleecker, Anthony L. and Mary (Offsite-box 17)
    - Blenker, Louis (Offsite-box 17)
    - Bliss (Offsite-box 17)
    - Blodgett (Offsite-box 17)
    - Bloomfield (Offsite-box 17)
    - Blunt, James G. (Offsite-box 17)
    - Boker (Offsite-box 17)
    - Bolton, Reginald Pelham (Offsite-box 17)
    - Bonaparte (Offsite-box 17)
    - Bond (Offsite-box 17)
    - Bonheur, Rosa (Offsite-box 17)
    - Boone (Offsite-box 17)
    - Booth (Offsite-box 17)
    - Booth, John Wilkes (Offsite-box 17)
    - Borden (Offsite-box 18)
    - Boscawen, Edward (Offsite-box 18)
    - Botts (Offsite-box 18)
    - Boutwell, George (Offsite-box 18)
    - Bowditch (Offsite-box 18)
    - Bowen (Offsite-box 18)
    - Boyd (Offsite-box 18)
    - Braddock, Edward (Offsite-box 18)
    - Bradish, Luther (Offsite-box 18)
    - Bradley (Offsite-box 18)
    - Brady (Offsite-box 18)
    - Bragg, Braxton (Offsite-box 18)
    - Brant, Joseph (Offsite-box 18)
    - Breckenridge/Breckinridge (Offsite-box 18)
    - Breese (Offsite-box 18)
    - Breun (Offsite-box 18)
    - Brewster (Offsite-box 18)
    - Briggs (Offsite-box 18)
    - Bright (Offsite-box 18)
    - Bromfield (Offsite-box 18)
    - Brooke (Offsite-box 18)
    - Brooks (Offsite-box 18)
    - Brown (2 folders) (Offsite-box 19)
    - Brown, B. Gratz (Offsite-box 19)
    - Brown, Charles B. (Offsite-box 19)
    - Brown, John and wife (Offsite-box 19)
    - Brownell (Offsite-box 19)
    - Browning, Robert and Elizabeth Barrett (Offsite-box 19)
    - Brownlow, William G. (Offsite-box 19)
    - Bryant (Offsite-box 19)
    - Bryant, William Cullen (Offsite-box 19)
    - Bryant, William Jennings (Offsite-box 19)
    - Buchanan, James (Offsite-box 19)
    - Buck (Offsite-box 20)
    - Buckingham (Offsite-box 20)
    - Buckley (Offsite-box 20)
    - Buckner (Offsite-box 20)
    - Buell (Offsite-box 20)
    - Bunyan (Offsite-box 20)
    - Burgoyne, John (Offsite-box 20)
    - Burke (Offsite-box 20)
    - Burnet (Offsite-box 20)
    - Burnham (Offsite-box 20)
    - Burns (Offsite-box 20)
    - Burns, Robert (Offsite-box 20)
    - Burnside, Ambrose G., and wife (Offsite-box 20)
    - Burr, Aaron and Theodosia, and wives (Offsite-box 20)
    - Burroughs, John (Offsite-box 20)
    - Burton (Offsite-box 20)
    - Burton, Thomas J. (Offsite-box 20)
    - Butler (Offsite-box 21)
    - Butler, Benjamin F. (Offsite-box 21)
    - Butler, Benjamin Franklin (Offsite-box 21)
    - Butler, Charles B. (Offsite-box 21)
    - Butler, Ellen Grenville (Offsite-box 21)
    - Butler, Franklin Crosby (Offsite-box 21)
    - Butler, Mary Howard (Offsite-box 21)
    - Butler, Nicholas Murray (Offsite-box 21)
    - Butler, Willard Parker (Offsite-box 21)
    - Butterfield, Daniel (Offsite-box 21)
    - Buxton (Offsite-box 21)
    - Byng, George, Lord Torrington (Offsite-box 21)
    - Byng, John (Offsite-box 21)
    - Byron, George Gordon (Offsite-box 21)
    - Ca-Cz miscellaneous (37 folders) (Offsite-box 22)
    - Cable, George Washington (Offsite-box 26)
    - Cadwalader (Offsite-box 26)
    - Caesar family (Offsite-box 26)
    - Caldwell (Offsite-box 26)
    - Calhoun, John C., and wife (Offsite-box 26)
    - Calvert, Cecil and George (Offsite-box 26)
    - Cameron (Offsite-box 26)
    - Cameron, Simon (Offsite-box 26)
    - Cammann family (Offsite-box 26)
    - Campbell (Offsite-box 26)
    - Campbell, Thomas (Offsite-box 26)
    - Carey (Offsite-box 26)
    - Carleton, Guy (Offsite-box 26)
    - Carlin (Offsite-box 26)
    - Carlson, Arthur B. and family (Offsite-box 26)
    - Carlyle, Thomas (Offsite-box 27)
    - Carman, Richard (Offsite-box 27)